Guide to the J. Claude Evans Family Papers, 1930-2002 RL.10008
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Claude Evans family papers
1930-2002
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Evans family
RL.10008
30 Linear Feet
J. Claude Evans was a United Methodist minister who served in South Carolina, Texas, and North Carolina along with his wife, Maxilla. He edited the South Carolina Methodist Advocate from 1952 to 1957, and was chaplain at Southern Methodist University in Dallas from 1957 until his retirement from the ministry in 1982. The majority of the family's papers relate to the pastoral and counseling career of J. Claude Evans, and include drafts and copies of his sermons, articles, columns, and other writings from the 1940s through the early 2000s on wide-ranging topics such as Christianity, spirituality, abortion, race, sexuality, sexism, nature, equality, aging, and violence. The papers also include some personal materials, correspondence, genealogy, notes and printed materials from his many professional activities, and Evans' subject files. There is a small amount of material created and collected by Maxilla, J. Claude's wife, largely relating to her bird watching and breeding of songbirds in Texas and North Carolina.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The J. Claude Evans Family Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2006.
Historical Note
J. Claude Evans was born in Anderson, SC, in 1917. He graduated from Wofford College and Duke Divinity School (1940) and became an ordained member of the South Carolina Methodist Conference. He served pastorates in Columbia, Clemson, and Walhalla, was a Navy chaplain in 1944-45, edited the S.C. Methodist Advocate from 1952-57 (for which he wrote many editorials on issues like race and McCarthyism), and served as the university chaplain at SMU from 1957-82. In retirement he wrote regular columns for the Waynesville, N.C., Mountaineer, primarily on social justice issues. He also had a substantial practice in family counseling.
His papers consist of large numbers of sermons, articles (he wrote regularly for the Christian Century in the 1960s and 1970s), and columns as well as some correspondence. He began speaking out on racial justice in 1942 with a sermon attacking the biological idea of race that got him barred from the pulpit of Washington Street Methodist Church in Columbia. In the early 1970s, before Roe v. Wade, he was active in the Clergy Consultation on Abortion, an abortion referral network, and he wrote a number of sermons and columns on gay rights, drawing on the experience of having a lesbian sister.
Maxilla Evans was born in 1917 in Palmyra, North Carolina. She first attended the N.C. Women's College in Greensboro, but graduated from N.C. State University in 1940 with a degree in landscape architecture. She and J. Claude Evans married that year and had four children. Maxilla was an active birder and gardener, and raised prize-winning canaries along with collecting rare and unique Appalachian plants. She help found and create the Corneille Bryan Native Garden at Lake Junaluska, North Carolina. The couple later relocated to Asheville. J. Claude Evans died on September 7, 2007. Maxilla Evans died on December 25, 2007.
Collection Overview
This collection has been arranged into nine series, most of which reflect the life and work of J. Claude Evans. One series, the Maxilla Evans Materials series, relates exclusively to Maxilla Evans' interests in birding, bird breeding, and horticulture, and also includes some of her writings, correspondence, family history, and other collected materials.
One of the largest series relating to J. Claude Evans is the Sermons series, with sermons arranged alphabetically by title. Files in this series reflect Evans' own arrangement of his papers, which typically include sermon copies with annotations punctuating his delivery and emphasis, notes and research about the subject, lists of when the sermon was preached and at which church, and occasionally bulletins from various services. Sermon topics varied widely, with many fairly liberal sermons on controversial issues like women's rights, abortion, racism, drugs, communism, atheism, and homosexuality.
Another large component of the collection is the Subject Files series, collected by Evans to support his research and writings both as a pastor and a columnist. This series includes many clippings, notes, and other materials curated by Evans, and is also arranged alphabetically by subject.
Evans' Correspondence is arranged into alphabetical and thematic sub-series. Most of the correspondence is sorted alphabetically by correspondent, unless Evans purposefully collected and grouped a batch of letters together under another heading; usually these are letters he received in reaction to an article or sermon on controversial issues like race, abortion, and so on. Evans also segregated letters between him and Maxilla during World War II and his other travels. These headings are listed beneath the alphabetical correspondence files.
Evans' Personal Files relate to largely non-pastoral or counseling topics, including his childhood, marriage and family, military life, family history and photographs, and scrapbooks. The Pastoral Activities series includes Evans' materials from various churches and community organizations such as the Intentional Growth Center, as well as counseling and theology professional memberships. This series also includes a small amount of audiocassettes recording Evans' devotionals, seminar workshops, and other speaking engagements. Finally, the Courses and Notes series contains most of Evans' handwritten notes from the many seminars, workshops, and classes he both took and taught during his long career as a pastor and counselor.
Evans' prolific Writings began while he was a student in the 1930s and continued until he retired from writing columns for the Waynesville Mountaineer in 2000. The series is arranged into Published Articles, Drafts, and Prayers. Within the Drafts are Evans' multiple working copies of his Mountaineer columns, arranged alphabetically by title. (Copies of the published versions are filed chronologically under Published Articles.) Additional reactions to Evans' writings can also be found in the Correspondence series. The Prayers are unsorted, except for a batch of prayer cards organized by subject, kept by Evans during his chaplaincy at SMU.
The Printed Materials series contains texts both written, edited, and collected by Evans, including college yearbooks, bound copies of the Methodist Advocate dating from his tenure as editor, and other books that reference Evans and his work as an abortion counselor.
Waynesville (N.C.) -- Social life and customs; Dallas (Tex.) -- Social life and customs; Bird watching -- North Carolina; Bird watching -- Texas; Racism -- United States; Abortion counseling; Pastoral counseling; Gay rights -- United States; Methodist Church -- Southern States -- Clergy; Abortion -- Religious aspects; Scrapbooks; Race -- Religious aspects -- Methodist Church; Sound recordings; Sermons; Evans family; Evans, Maxilla; Evans, Joseph Claude; United Methodist Church (U.S.); Southern Methodist University
- Sermons, 1932-2001, 11 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains sermons written and preached by J. Claude Evans throughout his career. The materials include handwritten and typed drafts, notes, and some reference materials such as magazine or newspaper clippings. Many of the sermons were revised and reused throughout the decades, and Evans's own lists of the places and dates he preached particular sermons are often included with the text.
  Evans's sermons address a broad range of subjects. Most of them address contemporary socio-political topics, issues of faith and Christianity, or, frequently, both. Examples of sermons that address the Christian faith directly include seasonal, sacramental, or celebratory topics such as "Advent Joy," "What Can I Believe about Baptism?" or a variety of sermons for weddings. Also included are sermons about belief and the place of religion in modern life, such as "Liturgy and Life" and "Science and Religion: A Needless Argument."
  More numerous are the sermons which address contemporary socio-political issues and current events. These sermons address abortion (as in "The Problem of Unwanted Pregnancies"), race ("Racism: A Contemporary Wilderness"), women ("Are Women Really Persons?"), homosexuality ("My Sister Was a Lesbian"), communism and politics (as in "Marxist Communism and the Christian Faith"), marriage and family ("My Son Was a Runaway" and "Enduring Marriage: An Impossible Possibility") and, later, dementia and illness.
  The sermons are filed alphabetically by title.
  - Sermons: A-C (Box 1)
  - Sermons: C-D (Box 2)
  - Sermons: E-G (Box 3)
  - Sermons: G-I (Box 4)
  - Sermons: I-L (Box 5)
  - Sermons: L-M (Box 6)
  - Sermons: N-P (Box 7)
  - Sermons: P-S (Box 8)
  - Sermons: S-V (Box 9)
  - Sermons: W (Box 10)
  - Sermons: W-Y (Box 11)
- Subjects, 1932-2002, 13 boxes
  The Subjects series includes an assortment of newspaper and magazine articles, advertisements, and other clippings, including materials from numerous religious periodicals such as the Methodist Advocate. Evans collected much of this material while researching subjects for his sermons and columns. The subjects reflect current events, especially of the 1960s and 70s, as well as theological issues.
  Subjects contained within the series can for the most part be grouped under three categories; current events, counseling, and faith or religion. A sample of subject files from the current events group include information on the Berkeley riots, capital punishment, the draft, energy, homosexuality, J.F.Kennedy's assassination, modern medicine and health care, and playboys and playmates, among many others. There are additional materials related to the abortion issue that Evans collected in an album, which is included in the Personal series.
  Subjects pertaining to counseling include files on anxiety, apathy, death and hope, depression, grief, hypnotism, and suicide. Subjects regarding faith include documents on the bible, Catholicism, church and state, evangelism, vocation, and files on other pastors such as Billy Graham, among others. There are also a number of files labeled "Column Ideas" which include materials that Evans had specifically put aside as sources for his writing.
  The Subject series is filed alphabetically by subject.
  - A-Anger (Box 12)
  - Apostolic-Christ (Box 13)
  - Christian-Columns (Box 14)
  - Columns-Counseling (Box 15)
  - Counter Culture-Ecology (Box 16)
  - Education-G (Box 17)
  - H-Jewish (Box 18)
  - Job-Marriage (Box 19)
  - Marxist-O (Box 20)
  - P-Repentance (Box 21)
  - Resurrection-Sexuality (Box 22)
  - Shakespeare-Wink (Box 23)
  - Women-Z (Box 24)
- Correspondence, 1926-2002, 3 boxes
  The Correspondence series contains letters, greeting cards, postcards, notes, and telegrams sent to and by J. Claude Evans throughout his lifetime. These letters include personal correspondence such as Christmas cards, correspondence with Evans's wife, Maxilla, and other family members, and a number of letters exchanged while Evans was stationed at various locations while serving in the navy and during later trips to Central and Eastern Europe. For additional personal letters to Evans's family, please see the scrapbooks and albums in the Personal series.
  The majority of the letters concern professional matters, such as Evans's sermons, appointments at Clemson, SMU, and the Mountaineer, correspondence regarding Evans's counseling practice, and exchanges with colleagues at various institutions. Some letters were written to Evans in response to controversial subjects as abortion or race which he addressed in his sermons and columns.
  The Correspondence series is filed alphabetically by the correspondent's last name with the exception of certain file folders which contain correspondence grouped based on topic, which are included at the end of the list below.
  - Correspondence: A-M (Box 25)
  - Correspondence: N-Z (Box 26)
  - Germany: Letters to Family, 1966-1967 (Box 26)
  - Correspondence Re: The Christian Century (Box 26)
  - Correspondence Re: Article "Together" (Box 26)
  - Correspondence Re: Various Articles and Sermons (Box 26)
  - Christmas Cards (Box 27)
  - Correspondence from Unnamed Correspondents (Box 27)
  - Correspondence Re: Sermons on Race, 1942-1944 (Box 27)
  - Correspondence Re: Accusations of Communism, 1960s (Box 27)
  - Correspondence Re: Abortion (Box 27)
  - Childhood Letters to Sister Mary ("Polly"), 1926-1932 (Box 27)
  - Letters to and from Maxilla Evans during WWII (Box 27)
  - Correspondence with R.C. Griffith (Box 27)
  - Correspondence Re: Articles (Rejection notices, etc.) (Box 27)
  - Correspondence Re: Articles (General) (Box 27)
  - Correspondence Re: Sermons on J.F. Kennedy's death, "Meaning of a Tragic Death" (Box 27)
  - Family Correspondence, 1945-1962 (Box 27)
  - Letters to Maxilla Evans during Europe Trip, 1973 (Box 27)
- Personal, 1926-2002, 7 boxes
  The Personal series includes documents from J. Claude Evans's youth, military and pastoral careers, and family life. These materials are Evans's passports, official navy orders and records, information on his education, a childhood diary, awards and certificates, court records, and articles about Evans, among other documents. The series contains photographs from J. Claude's youth and years at Duke as well as later, professional photos. A large scrapbook contains wartime letters and postcards from J. Claude to Maxilla while he was stationed abroad and an extensive scrapbook Evans created with articles and other notes regarding the abortion debate. The Personal series also includes a leather-bound bible that is inscribed by Evans in 1944 and has a note that it belonged to a T. Ligau c. 1896.
  There are also a number of files pertaining to the Evans family's genealogy, including extensive research into both J. Claude and Maxilla Evans's family history. This includes a large photo album from the early twentieth century.
  - Articles about Evans (Box 28)
  - Awards and Certificates (Box 28)
  - CD Collection Records (Box 28)
  - Claude Evans Passports (Box 28)
  - Court Documents (Box 28)
  - Death of Joseph Evans (Father), 1952 (Box 28)
  - Fiftieth Wedding Anniversary, 1990 (Box 28)
  - Evans Cabin (Repairs, etc.) (Box 28)
  - J. Claude Evans's Childhood Diary, 1928 (Box 28)
  - J. Claude Evans Education (Box 28)
  - Foxfire Theatrical Production, 1982 (Box 28)
  - Margaret M. Evans Will and Estate (Box 28)
  - Military Orders, U.S. Navy Reserve (Box 28)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 28)
  - Miscellaneous Articles (Box 28)
  - Navy Chaplaincy (Box 28)
  - Persona Vitae (Box 28)
  - Private Practice for Personal Counseling (Box 28)
  - Robert Everett Evans Education and Selective Service (Box 29)
  - SMU Chaplaincy Appointment, 1957 (Box 29)
  - SMU Retirement, 1979 (Box 29)
  - Unicef (Box 29)
  - Veteran's Administration (Box 29)
  - Evans Family Genealogy: Articles on Evans/Everett Families (Box 29)
  - Evans Family Genealogy: Family Trees, Photo, and Notes (Box 29)
  - Evans Family Genealogy: "The Everetts of Martin County, N.C." Bound Genealogical Research (Box 29)
  - Evans Family Genealogy: Family Reunion, 1991 (Box 29)
  - Family Photographs (Box 29)
  - Hamilton-Everett House (Box 29)
  - John Evans Re: Stanley Hicks (Box 29)
  - Golden Age of Texas M.S.M. Reunion (Photographs) (Box 29)
  - Maxilla Evans Genealogy (Box 29)
  - Miscellaneous Photographs (Box 29)
  - Professional Photographs (Box 29)
  - Weddings (Box 29)
  - Evans Leather-bound Bible, 1944 (Box 30)
  - Wartime Scrapbook of Letters to Maxilla, 1945 (Box 31)
  - Photograph Album (Youth and Duke University) (Box 32)
  - Family Photograph Album (Early Twentieth Century) (Box 33)
  - Scrapbook of Abortion Clippings and Articles (Box 34)
- Writings, 1930-2002, 5 boxes
  The Writings series includes three subseries: Published Articles and Columns -primarily J. Claude Evans's writings for The Mountaineer, Drafts, and Prayers. These materials include Evans's writings throughout his career for various pastoral and professional purposes.
  The Published Articles and Columns subseries is filed alphabetically by the name of the newspaper or periodical in which Evans's writing was published. The Drafts subseries is filed alphabetically by title, with drafts for columns listed under "C" and then listed alphabetically by title within the folder.
  - Published Articles and Columns, 1939-1992 (Box 35)
    - Christian Horizons Column, 1939: "Applying the Spiritual Dynamic" (Box 35)
    - Southern Christian Advocate Published Columns, 1941-1948 (Box 35)
    - The Pulpit Published Columns, 1944 and 1951 (Box 35)
    - Greenville News, 1955 (Box 35)
    - Christian Century Articles and Columns, 1971 and 1979 (Box 35)
    - South Carolina United Methodist Advocate, 1971 and 1987 (Box 35)
    - Charlotte Observer, 1983: "Abortion: A Sad and Tragic Choice" (Box 35)
    - The Christian Ministry, 1986 (Box 35)
    - The Mountaineer Published Columns, 1987-1992, 6 folders (Box 35)
    - The Mountaineer Published Columns, 1993-2000, 8 folders (Box 36)
    - The Mountaineer Published Columns, undated (Box 36)
    - Notes about Evans's Mountaineer Columns (Box 36)
    - Letters to the Editor Re: Evans's Mountaineer Columns (Box 36)
  - Article and Column Drafts (Box 36)
    - Abortion is a Pastoral Concern, Re: SB-553, 1971 (Box 36)
    - Accidental Death and the Easter Faith (Box 36)
    - Article Drafts by Evans, 1960s (Box 36)
    - Assorted Lectures and Notes (Box 36)
    - Civil Rights and the Republican Strategy to Crack the Solid South (Box 36)
    - The Conflict of Race: Washington St. Church "Blowup", 1942-1944 (Box 36)
    - Counselors Talk (Box 36)
    - Column Drafts, 8 folders (Box 37)
      Arrangement note
      Arranged alphabetically by column title. Some folders include many versions of the same column, each with different edits or notes by Evans.
    - Holiness Movement in the Methodist Church with Especial Attention to the S.C. Conference, 1878-1900 (Box 38)
    - Lectures on Marriage Counseling (Box 38)
    - E.R. Mason Article: An Organized Vicious Minority Versus an Unorganized Gullible Majority, No Date (Box 38)
    - Roman Catholic Views on Church and State Relationships (Box 38)
    - Second Fall of Man, 1965 and No Date (Box 38)
    - Sex and Christian Morality (Box 38)
    - A Story in Memory of Frank F. Gumpert (Box 38)
    - A Theological Trek (Box 38)
    - This is the South, Suh/A Key to Understanding the South (Box 38)
    - Paul Tillich Speech (Box 38)
    - What is Life For? (Population Article), c. 1970 (Box 38)
    - The Word, the World, and the Sacrament, 1963 (Box 38)
    - Youth Culture Lecture, Dallas, 1972 (Box 38)
  - Prayers (Box 39)
    - SMU Prayers, thematically, 2 folders (Box 39)
    - Rotary Prayers (Box 39)
    - Prayers, 4 folders (Box 39)
- Printed Materials, 1800-1990s, 5 boxes
  The Printed Materials Series includes a range of materials saved and collected by J. Claude Evans. It contains assorted clippings, publications, and articles on theology, women's issues, and LGBT. The series also includes bound copies of the South Carolina Methodist Advocate dating from his time as editor (1952-1957), and bound bulletins from Southern Methodist University dating from his time as chaplain (1959-1979). Other materials include Evans' yearbooks and those from his sister, Eugenia (Gene), from the 1930s and early 1940s. This series also includes books, written by others, which mention Evans and his pastoral and counseling work.
  - Ritual books (Box 40)
  - Apathy, Apostasy, and Apostles book jacket (with Evans illustration on cover) (Box 40)
  - Seminar programs, 1978-1991 (Box 40)
  - Art exhibitions (Box 40)
  - Liturgies, 1961-1972 (Box 40)
  - Duke Divinity School: Christian Horizons, 1938-1940 (Box 40)
  - Miscellaneous monographs to study (Box 40)
  - Articles reprinted from South Carolina Methodist Advocate, 1950s, 3 folders (Box 40)
  - Assorted publications and clippings by other authors (not by Evans), 8 folders (Box 41)
  - Bound copies of the Methodist Magazine, 1800 (Box 42)
  - SMU bound bulletins, 1959-1979 (Box 43)
  - Books mentioning Evans re: abortion and Roe v. Wade (Box 43)
  - Miscellaneous books from Evans' library, including some with inscriptions to him (Box 43)
  - Bohemian yearbooks (J. Claude Evans) from Wofford College, 1935-1937 (Box 44)
  - Bonhomie yearbooks (Eugenia Evans) from Furman University, 1938-1941 (Box 44)
  - Bound copies of the Methodist Advocate, 1952-1957 (Box 45)
- Pastoral Activities, 1940s-2000, 4 boxes
  The Pastoral Activities series includes materials from J. Claude Evans' professional work as a pastor and counselor to communities throughout the South. Some materials relate to his professional affiliations and memberships; others to his counseling work in Dallas and Waynesville; and others to specific churches where he ministered or preached.
  Also includes a box of 30 cassette tapes of Evans speaking and preaching. These tapes are closed to researchers until use copies can be made.
  - AAMFT convocation, Chicago, 1997 (Box 46)
  - American Association of Pastoral Counselors, including Kanuga, 1996-1998, 4 folders (Box 46)
  - Altrusa - Rotary Committee (Box 46)
  - Clergy consultation on abortion (Box 46)
  - Committee on Resolutions for the South Carolina United Methodist Conference, re: homosexuality, 1998 (Box 46)
  - Cornerstone Class, First United Methodist, Waynesville, NC (Box 46)
  - Dallas Community Campus Ministry (Box 46)
  - Evolution of Psychotherapy, 1970 (Box 46)
  - Faith Methodist Church retreat, 1995 (Box 46)
  - Fall Fling re: dementia, 1999 (Box 46)
  - First National Conference on Christians' Economic Responsibility... "A Theology of Vocation" (Box 46)
  - Growth Group, 1974 (Box 46)
  - Intentional Growth Center (Box 46)
  - Intentional Growth Center: Beyond Competition: Clergy caring for clergy (Box 46)
  - "Iron Curtain" Marxist-Christian seminar trip, 1973 (Box 46)
  - Liturgies, 1964 (Box 46)
  - Lovers Lane Methodist Church (Box 47)
  - NAPC Chicago, 1978 (Box 47)
  - NCAPC, 1993-1994, 2 folders (Box 47)
  - NW Texas Conference Pastor's Retreat (Box 47)
  - Pairing Marathon, SMU, 1976 (Box 47)
  - PBS materials, 2 folders (Box 47)
  - Photographs, including weddings, 2 folders (Box 47)
  - Reconciling Ministries (Box 47)
  - Religious Life Philosophy report, SMU (Box 47)
  - Roundtable re: higher education, SMU (Box 47)
  - The Sin of Being Single, November 1979 (Box 47)
  - St. Luke UMC, Walhalla, SC (Box 47)
  - SC Clergy for Choice, 1991 (Box 47)
  - Underwood grant, 1974 (Box 47)
  - University Church, SMU, 1978-1980 (Box 47)
  - Vocation Study Group (Box 47)
  - Washington Street Church, SC (Box 47)
  - WNC materials (Box 47)
  - Working on your Marriage, 1993 (Box 47)
  - Cassette tapes (Box 48)
    Devotionals, seminar and conference presentations, and other tapes (include one with a debate on abortion). AV Identification numbers: RL0008-CS-0001 through 0026 and RL0008-MCS-0001 through 0004. Original audiovisual materials are CLOSED to researchers until use copies are made. Contact Research Services in advance.
  - Certificates and awards (some oversize) (Box 49)
- Maxilla Evans Materials, 1970s-1990s, 3 boxes
  Maxilla Evans' papers largely center on her bird watching, horticulture, and other nature conservation activities in Texas and North Carolina. There are also drafts of her writings, family correspondence, and research materials on Christianity, feminism, and Quakerism. She also collected genealogy and family history materials.